<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>insert</refname>

    <refpurpose>Insert values from a source array into a target
    array.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <synopsis>insert(<replaceable>array</replaceable>,<replaceable>named_array</replaceable>);</synopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>The insert operator has two effects. One effect is to update the
    target array by inserting values from the source array. This means that
    the insert operator is a write operator, like the store() and
    redimension_store() operators.</para>

    <para>The other effect is to produce a result array identical to the
    updated target array. This means that you can use the insert operator as
    an operand of other SciDB operators, although using the insert() operator
    inside any other write operator--i.e., store() or redimension_store()--can
    yield unpredictable results.</para>

    <para>The source array and target array must be compatible. For the insert
    operator, compatible means the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The source and target arrays must have the same number of
        attributes.</para>

        <para>(Note: To the insert operator, attribute names are immaterial;
        the attribute names in the source and target arrays need not match.
        Rather, the first attribute of the source corresponds to the first
        attribute of the target; the second to the second, etc.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the left-to-right ordering of attributes in each array, each
        pair of corresponding attributes must have the same datatype and the
        same null/not null setting.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The source and target arrays must have the same number of
        dimensions.</para>

        <para>(Here too, the names are immaterial. Source dimensions and
        target dimensions correspond based on the left-to-right order of
        dimensions.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the left-to-right ordering of dimensions in each array, each
        pair of corresponding dimensions must have the same chunk size, chunk
        overlap, and dimension starting index.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For each cell location of the target array, the insert operator
    writes values according to the following rules:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If the corresponding cell location of the source array is empty,
        the insert operator does not write anything. At that cell location of
        the target array, an empty cell would remain empty, null values would
        remain null, and other values would remain unchanged.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If the corresponding cell location of the source array is non
        empty, the insert operator changes the corresponding cell of the
        target array to match the value of the source. Note that this means
        that null values in the source can overwrite non-null values in the
        target. Note that it also means that if the cell location of the
        target array was initially empty, it will be non-empty after the
        insert operation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>The AFL insert operator provides the same functionality as the AQL
      <code><command>INSERT INTO</command></code> ... statement.</para>
    </note>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Example</title>

    <informalexample>
      <para>These examples show the behavior of the insert() operator.</para>
    </informalexample>

    <informalexample>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Show array A. Note that row 1 has only empty cells, row 2 has
          only null values, and row 3 has only non-null values.<para><programlisting>AQL% <command>SELECT</command> * <command>FROM</command> A
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(),()],
[(null),(null),(null)],
[("a7"),("a8"),("a9")]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Show array B. Note that column 1 has only empty cells, column
          2 has only null values, and column 3 has only non-null
          values.<para><programlisting>AQL% <command>SELECT</command> * <command>FROM</command> B
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(null),("b3")],
[(),(null),("b6")],
[(),(null),("b9")]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Insert values from A into B. <para><programlisting>AFL% insert(A,B)
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(null),("b3")],
[(null),(null),(null)],
[("a7"),("a8"),("a9")]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Show the versions of B. Version 1 is the original version of
          B. Version 2 is the version resulting from the insert operation of
          the previous step. <para><programlisting>AQL% <command>SELECT</command> * <command>FROM</command> versions(B)
  </programlisting><screen>{VersionNo} version_id,timestamp
{1} 1,"2012-10-09 18:29:21"
{2} 2,"2012-10-09 18:29:22"
</screen></para></para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Insert values from B (the original version of B--unchanged by
          the previous insert operation) into A<para><programlisting>AFL% insert (B@1, A)
  </programlisting><screen>[
[(),(null),("b3")],
[(null),(null),("b6")],
[("a7"),(null),("b9")]
]</screen></para></para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </informalexample>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Limitations</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In both the source and the target array, each dimension must
        have datatype int64.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For each corresponding pair of dimensions in the source and
        target:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>If the target dimension is bounded, the source dimension
            must also be bounded and the respective upper bounds must be
            equal.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the target dimension is unbounded, the source dimension
            can be unbounded.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the target dimension is unbounded and the source
            dimension is bounded, the source dimension's chunk size must
            divide the source dimension's size evenly.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
