<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"docbookV4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch01" remap="h1">
  <title>Introduction to SciDB</title>

  <para>SciDB is an all-in-one data management and advanced analytics
  platform. It provides massively scalable complex analytics inside a
  next-generation database with data versioning to support the needs of
  commercial and scientific applications. SciDB is an open source software
  platform that runs on a grid of commodity hardware or in a cloud.</para>

  <para>Paradigm4 Enterprise SciDB with Paradigm4 Extensions is an enterprise
  distribution of SciDB with additional linear algebra operations, timeseries
  processing, high availability options, and client connector features.</para>

  <para>Unlike conventional relational databases designed around a row or
  column-oriented table data model, SciDB is an array database. The native
  array data model provides compact data storage and high performance
  operations on ordered data such as spatial (location-based) data, temporal
  (time series) data, and matrix-based data for linear algebra
  operations.</para>

  <para>This document is a User's Guide, written for scientists and developers
  in various application areas who want to use SciDB as their scalable data
  management and analytic platform.</para>

  <para>This chapter introduces the key technical concepts in SciDB—its array
  data model, basic system architecture including distributed data management,
  salient features of the local storage manager, and the system catalog. It
  also provides an introduction to SciDB's array languages—Array Query
  Language (AQL) and Array Functional Language (AFL)—and an overview of
  transactions in SciDB.</para>

  <sect1 remap="h2" xreflabel="array_data_model" xml:id="ArrayDataModel">
    <title>Array Data Model</title>

    <para>SciDB uses multidimensional arrays as its basic storage and
    processing unit. A user creates a SciDB array by specifying<emphasis>
    dimensions</emphasis> and<emphasis> attributes</emphasis> of the
    array.</para>

    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Dimensions</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>An n-dimensional SciDB array has dimensions <emphasis>d1</emphasis>,
    <emphasis>d2</emphasis>, ..., <emphasis>dn</emphasis>. The
    <emphasis>size</emphasis> of the dimension is the number of ordered values
    in that dimension. For example, a 2-dimensional array may have dimensions
    <emphasis>i</emphasis> and <emphasis>j</emphasis>, each with values (1, 2,
    3, ..., 10) and (1, 2, ..., 30) respectively.</para>

    <para>Basic array dimensions are 64-bit integers. SciDB also supports
    arrays with one or more noninteger dimensions, such as variable-length
    strings (<emphasis>alpha</emphasis>,<emphasis> beta</emphasis>,<emphasis>
    gamma</emphasis>, ...) or floating-point values (1.2, 2.76, 4.3, ...).
    Version 12.10 of SciDB and Paradigm4 support non-int64 dimensions only
    partially.</para>

    <para>When the total number of values or cardinality of a dimension is
    known in advance, the SciDB array can be declared with a<emphasis>
    bounded</emphasis> dimension. However, in many cases, the cardinality of
    the dimension may not be known at array creation time. In such cases, the
    SciDB array can be declared with an<emphasis> unbounded</emphasis>
    dimension.</para>

    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Attributes</emphasis>
    </para>

    <para>Each combination of dimension values identifies a cell or element of
    the array, which can hold multiple data values called attributes
    (<emphasis>a1</emphasis>, <emphasis>a2</emphasis>, ...,
    <emphasis>am</emphasis>). Each data value is referred to as an
    <emphasis>attribute</emphasis>, and belongs to one of the supported
    datatypes in SciDB.</para>

    <para>At array creation time, the user must specify:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>An array name.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Array dimensions. The name and size of each dimension must be
        declared.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Array attributes of the array. The name and data type of the
        each attribute must be declared.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Once you have created a SciDB database and defined the arrays, you
    must prepare and load data into it. Loaded data is then available to be
    accessed and queried using SciDB's built-in analytics capabilities.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 remap="h2" xml:id="BasicArchitecture">
    <title>Basic Architecture</title>

    <para>SciDB uses a <emphasis> shared-nothing</emphasis> architecture which
    is shown in the illustration below.</para>

    <informalfigure>
      <graphic align="center" contentdepth="500" depth="300"
               fileref="../graphics/scidb_arch.png" scale="80" valign="top"
               width="400"/>
    </informalfigure>

    <para>SciDB is deployed on a cluster of servers, each with processing,
    memory, and local storage, interconnected using a standard ethernet and
    TCP/IP network. Each physical server hosts a SciDB instance that is
    responsible for local storage and processing.</para>

    <para>External applications, when they connect to a SciDB database,
    connect to one of the instances in the cluster. While all instances in the
    SciDB cluster participate in query execution and data storage, one server
    is the <emphasis>coordinator</emphasis> and orchestrates query execution
    and result fetching. It is the responsibility of the coordinator instance
    to mediate all communication between the SciDB external client and the
    entire SciDB database. The rest of the system instances are referred to as
    <emphasis>worker</emphasis> instances and work on behalf of the
    coordinator for query processing.</para>

    <para>SciDB's scale-out architecture is ideally suited for hardware grids
    as well as clouds, where additional severs may be added to scale the total
    capacity.</para>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="ChunkingandScalability">
      <title>Chunking and Scalability</title>

      <para>When data is loaded, it is partitioned and stored on each instance
      of the SciDB database. SciDB uses<emphasis> chunking</emphasis>, a
      partitioning technique for multidimensional arrays where each instance
      is responsible for storing and updating a subset of the array locally,
      and for executing queries that use the locally stored data. By
      distributing data uniformly across all instances, SciDB is able to
      deliver scalable performance on computationally or I/O intensive
      analytic operations on very large data sets.</para>

      <para>The details of chunking are shown in this section. Remember that
      you do not need to manage chunk distribution beyond specifying chunk
      size.</para>

      <para>Chunking is specified for each array as follows. Each dimension of
      an array is divided into chunks. For example, an array with dimensions
      <literal>i</literal> and <literal>j</literal>, where
      <literal>i</literal> is of length 10 and chunk size 5 and
      <literal>j</literal> is of length 30 and chunk size 10 would be chunked
      as follows:</para>

      <graphic align="center" fileref="../graphics/chunked_dimensions.png"
               scale="70"/>

      <para>Chunks are stored allocated to instances of the SciDB cluster
      according to a hash-based scheme.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="ChunkAdjacency">
      <title>Chunk Overlap</title>

      <para>It is sometimes advantageous to have neighboring chunks of an
      array overlap with each other. Overlap is specified for each dimension
      of an array. For example, consider an array A as
      follows:<programlisting>A&lt;a: int32&gt;[i=1:10,5,1, j=1:30,10,5]</programlisting></para>

      <para>Array A has two dimensions, <literal>i</literal> and
      <literal>j</literal>. Dimension <literal>i</literal> is of length 10,
      chunk size 5, and had chunk overlap 1. Dimension <literal>j</literal>
      has length 30, chunk size 10, and chunk overlap 5. This overlap causes
      SciDB to store adjoining cells in each dimension from the
      <emphasis>overlap area</emphasis> in both chunks.</para>

      <para>Some advantages of chunk overlap are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Speeding up nearest-neighbor queries, where each chunk may
          need access to a few elements from its neighboring chunks,</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Detecting data clusters or data features that straddle more
          than one chunk.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>SciDB supports operators that can be used to add or change the
      chunk overlap within an existing array.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 remap="h2" xml:id="SciDBstoragemanagement">
    <title>SciDB Array Storage</title>

    <para>SciDB arrays consist of array chunk storage and array metadata
    stored in the system catalog. When arrays are created, updated, or
    removed, they are done using transactions. Transactions span array storage
    and the system catalog and ensure consistency of the overall database as
    queries are executed.</para>

    <para>The following sections describe SciDB's instance storage, system
    catalog, and transaction model.</para>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="StorageManagement">
      <title>Instance Storage</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Vertical partitioning</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Each local SciDB instance divides logical chunks of an array
            into per-attribute chunks, a technique referred to as
            <emphasis>vertical partitioning</emphasis>. All basic array
            processing steps—storage, query processing, and data transfer
            between instances—use single-attribute chunks. SciDB uses
            run-length encoding internally to compress repeated values or
            commonly occurring patterns typical in scientific applications.
            Frequently accessed chunks are maintained in an in-memory cache
            and accelerate query processing by eliminating expensive disk
            fetches for repeatedly accessed data.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Storage of array versions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>SciDB uses a "no overwrite" storage model. No overwrite
            means that data is never overwritten; each query that stores or
            updates existing arrays writes a new full chunk or a new
            <emphasis>delta chunk</emphasis>. Delta chunks are calculated by
            differencing the new version with the prior version and only
            storing the difference. The SciDB storage manager stores "reverse"
            deltas—this means that the most recent version is maintained as a
            full chunk, and prior versions are maintained as a list or chain
            of reverse deltas. The delta chain is stored in the "reserve"
            portion of each chunk, an additional area over and above the total
            size of the chunk. If the reserve area for the chunk fills up, a
            new chunk is allocated within the same segment or a new segment
            and linked into the delta chain.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Storage segments</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The local storage manager manages space allocation,
            placement, and reclamation within the local storage manager using
            <emphasis>segments</emphasis>. A storage segment is a contiguous
            portion of the storage file reserved for successive chunks of the
            same array. This is designed to optimize queries issued on a very
            large array to use sequential disk I/O and hence maximize the rate
            of data transfer during a query.</para>

            <para>Segments also serve as the unit of storage reclaim, so that
            as array chunks are created, written, and ultimately removed, a
            segment is reclaimed and reallocated for new chunks or arrays once
            all its member chunks have been removed. This allows for reuse of
            storage space.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Transient storage</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>SciDB uses temporary data files or "scratch space" during
            query execution. This is specified during initialization and
            start-up as the <literal>tmp-path</literal> configuration setting.
            Temporary files are managed using the operating system's
            <emphasis>tempfile</emphasis> mechanism. Data written to tempfile
            only last for the lifetime of a query. They are removed upon
            successful completion or abort of the query.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="LocalStorage">
      <title>SciDB System Catalog</title>

      <para>SciDB relies on a system catalog that is a repository of the
      following information:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Configuration and status information about the SciDB
            cluster,</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Array-related metadata such as array definitions, array
            versions, and associations between arrays and other related
            objects,</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Information about SciDB extensions, such as plug-in
            libraries containing user-defined objects, which are described in
            the section "Array Processing."</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>The system catalog in current versions of SciDB is implemented as
      PostgresSQL tables. The tables are shared between all SciDB instances
      within the cluster.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="transactions">
      <title>Transaction Model</title>

      <para>SciDB combines traditional ACID semantics with versioned, no
      overwrite array storage. When using versioned arrays, write transactions
      create new versions of the array—they do not modify pre-existing
      versions of the array.</para>

      <para>The scope of a transaction in SciDB is a single statement. Each
      statement involves many operations on one or more arrays. Ultimately,
      the transaction stores the result into a destination array.</para>

      <para>SciDB implements array-level locking. Locks are acquired at the
      beginning of a transaction and are used to protect arrays during
      queries. Locks are released upon completion of the query. If a query
      aborts, pending changes are undone at all instances in the system
      catalog, and the database is returned to a prior consistent
      state.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 remap="h2" xml:id="DatabaseConcepts">
    <title>Array Processing</title>

    <para>SciDB's query languages provide the basic framework for scalable
    array processing.</para>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="ArrayLanguages">
      <title>Array Languages</title>

      <para>SciDB provides two query language interfaces.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>AQL, the Array Query Language</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>AFL, the Array Functional Language</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>SciDB's Array Query Language (AQL) is a high-level declarative
      language for working with SciDB arrays. It is similar to the SQL
      language for relational databases, but uses an array-based data model
      and a more comprehensive analytical query set compared with standard
      relational databases.</para>

      <para>AQL represents the full set of data management and analytic
      capabilities including data loading, data selection and projection,
      aggregation, and joins.</para>

      <para>The AQL language includes two classes of queries:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Definition Language</emphasis>
          (DDL) : commands to define arrays and load data.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Manipulation Language</emphasis>
          (DML) : commands to access and operate on array data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>AQL statements are handled by the SciDB query compiler which
      translates and optimizes incoming statements into an execution
      plan.</para>

      <para>SciDB's Array Functional Language (AFL) is a functional language
      for working with SciDB arrays. AFL <emphasis>operators</emphasis> are
      used to compose queries or statements.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="BuildingBlocks">
      <title>Query Building Blocks</title>

      <para>There are four building blocks that you use to control and access
      your data. These building blocks are:<variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <emphasis>Operators</emphasis>
            </term>

            <listitem>
              <para>SciDB operators, such as join, take one or more SciDB
              arrays as input and return a SciDB array as output.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <emphasis>Functions</emphasis>
            </term>

            <listitem>
              <para>SciDB functions, such as sqrt, take scalar values from
              literals or SciDB arrays and return a scalar value.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <emphasis>Data types</emphasis>
            </term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Data types define the classes of values that SciDB can
              store and perform operations on.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>
              <emphasis>Aggregates</emphasis>
            </term>

            <listitem>
              <para>SciDB aggregates take an arbitrarily large set of values
              as input and return a scalar value.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist></para>

      <para>Any of these building blocks can be user-defined, that is, users
      can write new operators, data types, functions, and aggregates.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 remap="h3" xml:id="ACIDandTransactions">
      <title>Pipelined Array Processing</title>

      <para>When a SciDB query is issued, it is setup as a pipeline of
      operators. Operators are responsible for data processing and aggregation
      as well as intermediate data exchange and data storage.</para>

      <para>Execution begins when the client issues a request to fetch a chunk
      from the result array. Data is then scanned from array storage on all
      instances and streamed into and out of each operator one chunk at a
      time. This model of query execution is sometimes referred to as
      <emphasis>pull-based</emphasis> execution and the operators that use
      this model are called <emphasis>streaming</emphasis> operators. Unless
      required by the data processing algorithm, all SciDB operators are
      streaming operators. Some operators implement algorithms that require
      the entire array to be materialized in memory at all instances at once.
      These are referred to as <emphasis>materializing</emphasis>
      operators.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 remap="h2" xml:id="Clientsandconnectors">
    <title>Clients and Connectors</title>

    <para>The SciDB software package that you downloaded contains a special
    command line utility called<emphasis> iquery</emphasis> which provides an
    interactive Linux shell and supports both AQL and AFL. For more
    information about iquery, see Getting Started With SciDB
    Development.</para>

    <para>Client applications connect to SciDB using an appropriate connector
    package which implements the client-side of the SciDB client-server
    protocol. Once connected via the connector, the user may issue queries
    written in either AFL or AQL, and fetch the result of a query using an
    iterator interface.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 remap="h2" xml:id="ConventionsUsedinthisDocument">
    <title>Conventions Used in This Document</title>

    <para>Code to be typed in verbatim is shown in <literal>fixed-width
    font</literal>. Code that is to be replaced with an actual string is shown
    in<emphasis> italics</emphasis>. Optional arguments are shown in square
    brackets [].</para>

    <para>AQL commands are shown in <command>
        <code>FIXED-WIDTH BOLD CAPS</code>
      </command>. When necessary, a line of code may be preceded by the
    <code>AQL%</code> or <code>AFL%</code> prompt to show which language the
    query is issued from.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
